A Finding Aid to the American Art Research Council Records, 1935-1956, in the Archives of American Art AAA.amerartr
Archives of American Art
American Art Research Council records
bulk 1942-1947
1935-1956
AAA.amerartr
Archives of American Art
3 Linear feet
The records of the American Art Research Council, a cooperative research group headquartered at the Whitney Museum of American Art in New York, measure 3 linear feet and date from 1935 to 1956. The records include Chairman Juliana Force's correspondence, administrative correspondence, advisory committee files, miscellaneous administrative files, scattered financial records, and printed materials.
American Art Research Council.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 5 series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1942-1947 (1 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Advisory Committee, 1942-1947 (0.2 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 3: Administrative Records, 1935-1950 (0.9 linear feet; Boxes 2-3)
Series 4: Financial Records, 1942-1956 (0.7 linear feet; Boxes 3-4)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1942-1947 (0.2 linear feet; Box 5)
Biographical/Historical note
The American Art Research Council (AARC) was founded in 1942 when the Whitney Museum of American Art in New York City proposed that museums across the country establish a collaborative centralized organization for American art research. In April 1942, directors and representatives of 15 prominent museums met and founded the AARC.
Headquartered in and administered by the Whitney Museum, the AARC broadened its scope to include staff from over 30 museums and universities across the country. The organization formed a Committee on Research consisting of experts and scholars of American art that authenticated art, shared research records about artists, and conducted multiple surveys on various subjects. The AARC also facilitated researchers by sharing their information in catalogs and publications.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Washington, D.C. Research Facility.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of the collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reels N609-N614 at the Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the film does not represent the entirety of the collection and the arrangement on film does not match the arrangement of the collection as reflected in the finding aid.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The American Art Research Council records were donated by the Whitney Museum of American Art in 1978 as part of a larger donation of museum records.
Scope and Contents note
The records of the American Art Research Council, a cooperative research group headquartered at the Whitney Museum of American Art in New York, measure 3 linear feet and date from 1935 to 1956. The records include Chairman Juliana Force's correspondence, administrative correspondence, advisory committee files, miscellaneous administrative files, scattered financial records, and printed materials.
Correspondence consists of Chairman Juliana Force's correspondence with museums, curators, and others, in addition to general AARC correspondence on various subjects. The Advisory Committee series consists of correspondence, lists, reports, and meeting minutes.
Administrative records include assorted material such as reports on paintings owned by private individuals and art centers, correspondence and drafts on a special issue of Art in America, a bibliography, and surveys. Survey files consist of survey responses and indexes of results for several surveys conducted by the AARC.
Financial records consist of assorted material such as contribution records, ledgers, bank statements, and cancelled checks. Printed materials include clippings, academic journals, bulletins, and press releases.
Force, Juliana, 1876-1948; Whitney Museum of American Art.; Art--Study and teaching
- Correspondence, 1942-1947; Series 1; 1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence consists of Chairman Juliana Force's alphabetical correspondence and AARC subject correspondence.
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged as 2 subseries.
  1.1: Chairman Juliana Force Correspondence, 1942-1945
  1.2: Subject Correspondence, 1942-1947
  - Chairman Juliana Force Correspondence, 1942-1945; 1.1
    Chairman Juliana Force's correspondence is with museums, curators, and others concerning the formation and activities of the AARC.
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically.
    - Correspondence, A, 1942-1945 (Box 1-2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, B, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
    - Correspondence, C, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
    - Correspondence, D, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
    - Correspondence, E, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, F, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - Correspondence, G, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
    - Correspondence, H, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
    - Correspondence, I-J, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
    - Correspondence, K, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
    - Correspondence, L, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
    - Correspondence, M, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
    - Correspondence, N, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
    - Correspondence, O, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
    - Correspondence, P, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
    - Correspondence, R, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 32-33)
    - Correspondence, S, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 34-35)
    - Correspondence, T, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence, U-V, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Correspondence, V, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence, W, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 39-40)
    - Correspondence, Y-Z, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Subject Correspondence, 1942-1947; 1.2
    Subject correspondence concerns various AARC projects and activities, such as committees, publicity, photography, and printing.
    - College Art Association Liaison Committee, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Committee on Research, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Photography Records, 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 44-45)
    - Printing, 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Publicity, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Society of Architectural Historians, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Advisory Committee, 1942-1947; Series 2; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  Found here are files documenting the activities of the AARC Advisory Committee, including material on the establishment of the AARC, limited correspondence about meeting attendance, lists, reports, and meeting minutes.
  The material in this series is loosely grouped together by document type, then arranged chronologically within each grouping. Most of the original order and folder headings were retained.
  - Lists and Reports of AARC Establishment, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence about Meeting Attendance, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - Correspondence about Meeting, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Reports and Correspondence, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - Meeting Minutes and Reports, 1942-1947 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
- Administrative Records, 1935-1950; Series 3; 0.9 Linear feet Boxes 2-3
  Scattered administrative records include reports on paintings owned by private individuals and art centers, correspondence and drafts on an issue of Art in America about art research with the AARC, a bibliography of exhibitions and publications, "technical data" files, and multiple surveys. Survey files consist of responses and indexed results for AARC surveys of artists, museums, private collections, colleges, and universities.
  The material in this series are grouped together by document type, then arranged chronologically within each grouping.
  - Reports on Paintings (Box 2)
    - Portrait of Commodore Vanderbilt, 1935-1942 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Portraits Owned by C. V. Whitney, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Portrait Owned by G. Macculloch Miller, 1943-1946 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Walker Art Center, circa 1945 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Art in America Issue on Art Research (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, A-L, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, L-Z, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Original and Revised Manuscripts, circa 1945 (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - Bibliography on Books, Bulletins, and Exhibitions, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Technical Data File, circa 1946-1950 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - X-Rays and Scientific Material File, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Surveys (Box 3)
    - Artists Survey, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
    - Artist Responses to AARC Survey, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - AARC Artist List and Records of Work, 1943-1947 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Colleges and Universities Survey, 1943-1948 (Box 2, Folder 25-30)
    - College and University Index Cards, 1944-1948 (Box 2, Folder 31-32)
    - Museums and Art Institutions Survey Responses, A-B, 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Museum and Art Institutions Survey Responses, C-N, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Museums and Art Institutions Survey Responses, N-Z, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Museum Collections Index of Returned Forms, A-G, circa 1945 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Museum Collections Index of Returned Forms, H-N, circa 1945 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Museum Collections Index of Returned Forms, O-Z, circa 1945 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Private Collections Survey, 1936-1945 (Box 2, Folder 39-40)
  - Surveys (Box 3)
    - Private Collections Survey Index of Returned Forms, A-L, circa 1945 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Private Collections Survey Index of Returned Forms, L-Z, circa 1945 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Financial Records, 1942-1956; Series 4; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 3-4
  This series consists of contribution records, bank statements, bills, receipts, 3 checking account record books, and 2 ledgers.
  - Contribution Records and Correspondence, 1942-1948 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Contribution Records and Financial Statements, 1942-1947 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1942-1950 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - Executive Committee Resolutions about Finances, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Petty Cash Receipts, 1943-1946 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Checking Account Records Books, 1942-1956 (Box 3, Folder 10-12)
  - Ledger Account Books, 1942-1950 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Bank Statements and Cancelled Checks, 1942-1946 (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
  - Bank Statements, 1947-1956 (Box 4, Folder 6-9)
- Printed Material, 1942-1947; Series 5; 0.2 Linear feet Box 5
  Printed material includes publicity clippings about the AARC, academic journals, and a limited amount of bulletins and press releases.
  - The American Art Research Council Booklet, circa 1942 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - College Art Journal, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Art in America "Research in American Art" Issue, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "The Problem of Authenticity in American Art", 1942 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1942-1945 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Press Releases and Bulletins, 1942-1947 (Box 5, Folder 6)